<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>writing code, making music</title>
	<link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
	<description>Recent content on writing code, making music</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 19:15:53 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>A Year in Embedded Engineering</title>
		<link>http://localhost:1313/blog/a-year-in-embedded-engineering/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/a-year-in-embedded-engineering/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to do a bit of yapping, so if you want to skip to the good stuff, &lt;a href=&#34;#how-to-become-an-embedded-engineer&#34;&gt;click here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-year-not-in-embedded-engineering&#34;&gt;A Year (Not) in Embedded Engineering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2022, I began my software engineering career as an Associate Software Engineer at Canonical. I was working on
Mir: a window manager, compositor, and display server for Linux. Admittedly, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know too much about any of those
things when I was hired. I knew about Wayland; I knew it was a protocol for writing display servers, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know
much more than that. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure that in February 2022 I was capable of telling you what the difference between
a window manager, compositor, and display server were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first started using Ubuntu in 2010 on a hand-me-down Dell Inspiron from my mom. Specifically the 10.04 release, Lucid Lynx.
As a 10 year old kid, it blew my mind that people could write an entire operating system and maintain and distribute it at
no cost to the user. Even more, Ubuntu turned a single-core Celeron laptop which was borderline unusable on its original Windows
installation to a &lt;em&gt;blazingly fast&lt;/em&gt; machine that I could customize to my heart&amp;rsquo;s desire. I loaded that thing with Compiz effects
until its fans were begging for mercy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This laptop, almost just another brick in the wall of laptops at the recycling center, became my daily driver with which I explored
everything the FOSS community had to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to work with the people who made that crucial childhood memory a reality was quite intimidating. Here I am, a fresh computer
science graduate from Louisiana, in a hotel in Frankfurt playing Codenames with the lead of Ubuntu Desktop. I felt incredibly
under qualified working with the people whose names I had read in About pages twelve years prior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team who worked on Mir are some of the most brilliant minds I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had the pleasure of meeting. They pushed me to be the
best software engineer I could be. I call 2022 the year I experienced &amp;ldquo;trial by fire&amp;rdquo;. The team couldn&amp;rsquo;t have been more patient
as I floundered my way through PRs. The code reviews that year were master classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the patience and helpfulness of the team, I needed to work on something different. My ability to write code was improving,
but the problem domain was something that I was not very familiar with. I decided that if I was ever going to enjoy the process of
growing as a developer, I&amp;rsquo;d need to work on a project that was particularly interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-worlds-collide&#34;&gt;When Worlds Collide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far back as I can remember, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a tendency of getting quite hyperfixated on things. After Linux it was jailbreaking iOS
devices, then it was softmodding Wiis and OG XBOXes, while that was going on I was playing guitar in a rock band, then it was
PC building, making YouTube videos, DJing, expanding my musical palate, then software development, the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on this, as much as I seemed to be a completely different person every few months in my middle school and high school years,
I really was just oscillating between hyperfixating on one of two interests: computers or music. Sometimes both at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my senior year of college, I decided that what I really wanted to do was work on making tools for musicians with computers. I
applied to several companies and got some good advice on starting my career from many people in the industry, but no job offers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t very shocking. I rarely saw new grad positions opening up for software engineering jobs in music technology, so I was
applying to positions I was completely unqualified for. Understanding that C++ was the go-to language in the industry, I applied
to every job that I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; qualified for who used C++ in their stack, which got me that first job at Canonical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a year of experience on my resume, I applied for every software engineering position I was even remotely qualified for at
every audio technology company I could think of (about 35 companies total).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fender, who had an &lt;em&gt;embedded&lt;/em&gt; software engineering position open, interviewed me for the role. I had an Electrosmith Daisy that I had
very minimal experience with, but outside of that, I had zero experience with embedded systems. Between interviews, I was cramming
every search result I could find for I2S, I2C, UART, SAI, STM32, SPI, GPIO, and the other various acronyms that were in the job
listing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting the job, I was in &amp;ldquo;fake it &amp;rsquo;till you make it&amp;rdquo; mode for months. Luckily, while working in a domain that interests me
with incredible mentors who helped me get up to speed with the world of embedded engineering, the impostor syndrome that I&amp;rsquo;ve felt
since entering the workforce has started fading way. I don&amp;rsquo;t get everything, but I get &lt;strong&gt;it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-become-an-embedded-engineer&#34;&gt;How To Become An Embedded Engineer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to pivot into embedded engineering, you&amp;rsquo;re in luck. There are some incredibly high-quality and free resources
to get you on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of my favorites (in no particular order):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vivonomicon.com/2018/04/02/bare-metal-stm32-programming-part-1-hello-arm/&#34;&gt;Vivionomicon&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Bare Metal&amp;rdquo; STM32 Programming&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arguably the single most helpful writing I&amp;rsquo;ve come across on embedded programming. Walks you through many of the features
and design considerations one will come across when using STM32 products. He also gets into the nitty-gritty on how CubeMX
(STMicroelectronics&amp;rsquo; code generator for STM32 projects) generates peripheral access code and clock configurations. Also, his breakdown on linker
files were incredibly helpful in demystifying them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.thea.codes/the-most-thoroughly-commented-linker-script/&#34;&gt;Stargirl Flowers&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;The Most Thoroughly Commented Linker Script (Probably)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exactly what the title says. Great for people who know nothing about proper memory utilization and layout details on embedded
systems, such as myself about a month ago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(This post gets bonus points because she works on synthesizers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://makefiletutorial.com&#34;&gt;Makefile Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not specific to embedded programming, but Makefiles were as confusing as linker files to me until reading this&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@LowLevelLearning&#34;&gt;Low Level Learning on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of the most entertaining and digestible videos on embedded and systems programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@letsgetrusty&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Get Rusty on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not necessarily focused on embedded engineering, but a good channel to have in your toolbelt if you&amp;rsquo;re curious about Rust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-things-i-learned&#34;&gt;Some Things I learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of this post isn&amp;rsquo;t to be a course on embedded engineering, but I wanted to share some things I learned that I didn&amp;rsquo;t
know before entering this field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-peripherals&#34;&gt;1. Peripherals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re almost certainly going to have some kind of peripherals connected to the device you will be working on: buttons, screens,
speakers, LEDs, potentiometers, Bluetooth SoCs, proximity detectors, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing you&amp;rsquo;ll need to learn about is how peripherals transfer data from themselves to your MCU (Microcontroller Unit) and vice-versa.
Your MCU likely has ADCs (analog-to-digital converters) to convert analog inputs into data you can work with, DACs (context clues) to convert digital signals generated with
the MCU into analog voltages you can send to other peripherals, then it&amp;rsquo;ll have digital transport interfaces to transport different
types of digital data to and from the MCU: SPI, I2C, I2S, USB, UART, and a few more. It&amp;rsquo;s important to learn what all of these are,
what kinds of data they&amp;rsquo;re used to transmit, and have a general understanding of how they all work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-clocks&#34;&gt;2. Clocks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the cool things about working on embedded devices is having direct control over multiple clocks. I imagine every
software engineer knows that their PC&amp;rsquo;s CPU runs on a clock, and that the clock affects the speed of the device, but
in the embedded world, you get access to many more hardware clocks. These will be used for synchronizing data communication
between external chips and the MCU, determining the rate that ADCs are polling analog data, controlling Pulse Wave Modulation (PWM)
which is how you&amp;rsquo;ll end up controlling LED brightness, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On many STM32 devices, the peripheral clocks are controlled by one master clock which is then divided down into multiple subclocks.
These subclocks can have their frequencies either divided or multiplied to get to the frequency you need them to be. If you&amp;rsquo;re
using CubeMX to generate your MCU configurations, the Clock Configure page can look &lt;em&gt;wildly&lt;/em&gt; confusing, but once you understand
&lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it&amp;rsquo;s laid out that way (because you have clocks which are subdivisions of other clocks) it starts to make a lot more sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/A-Year-In-Embedded-Engineering/STM32_Clock_Config.png&#34; alt=&#34;whoa&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/q/40214987&#34;&gt;Image lifted from K. Mulier on Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-interrupts&#34;&gt;3. Interrupts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about this: analog signals can happen really quickly. &lt;em&gt;Really quickly&lt;/em&gt;. Blink and you missed a thousand of &amp;rsquo;em.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your application that has a main loop which gets run every millisecond could &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; catch something that fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why we have hardware interrupts which can run a function in your code &lt;em&gt;instantly&lt;/em&gt; after an analog signal is detected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be thinking, &amp;ldquo;Wait, but what happens when my precious main loop gets interrupted?&amp;rdquo; Well good news: the MCU can freeze
the stack where it&amp;rsquo;s at, create a &lt;em&gt;new stack&lt;/em&gt; to run the interrupt callback function on, then jump back onto the original one
once it&amp;rsquo;s done. Neat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As awesome as that is, there are some things you need to keep in mind when using hardware interrupts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re going to be getting &lt;em&gt;pulled out&lt;/em&gt; of your main app context every time one of these interrupts are hit, wherever
you were in execution. So you want whatever code is in the interrupt callback to be something that can get executed &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt;
so your code can get back to what it was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This one lead to one of the most confusing bugs I have ever seen.) If your hardware interrupt callback function needs to access
a piece of data that gets initialized at startup, keep in mind that &lt;em&gt;the interrupt may happen before that thing is initialized&lt;/em&gt;.
So if you had a class/method like &lt;code&gt;Power::shutDown()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Power&lt;/code&gt; gets initialized inside a class named &lt;code&gt;Main&lt;/code&gt;,
if your callback hits &lt;code&gt;Main::powerSwitchOffCallback()&lt;/code&gt; which calls &lt;code&gt;power.shutDown();&lt;/code&gt; keep in mind that &lt;code&gt;power&lt;/code&gt;
may not exist yet! Otherwise, your callback is going to hit a function pointer to nowhereland, and maybe this only happens
1/100,000 times the callback is hit because hardly anyone flips the power switch back off within the first 5ms of the device booting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-timers&#34;&gt;4. Timers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCUs will often have hardware timers which can be used to send a clock to peripherals or run callbacks at regular
intervals. If there&amp;rsquo;s anything that is time critical in your application where you need to guarantee that code will be run
every {period of time}, a timer can call an interrupt which pauses all other execution to run that code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-ram-layout&#34;&gt;5. RAM Layout&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite thing about embedded engineering is getting full access to the system&amp;rsquo;s resources. No pesky OS trying to tell me
how my processes are scheduled or how my memory is paged. This gives you the ability to do a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of cool optimizations without
the worry that an OS will come in and have some behavior that makes them impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get full control over what gets placed where in memory. Sometimes, you&amp;rsquo;ll be working with an external RAM or FLASH chip,
and you&amp;rsquo;ll need to be careful about what data goes there for access time/memory capacity reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-dma-dynamic-memory-access&#34;&gt;6. DMA (Dynamic Memory Access)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of having to pause your code to stop and listen to retrieve or send a packet to a peripheral, you can use on-board
DMA controllers which can always be copying data from a digital transport into a region in memory, which your application can
then read when it&amp;rsquo;s ready to read the received data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an absolute necessity when quickly and consistently transporting streams of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;epilogue&#34;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embedded software engineering is a very interesting field. There is something exciting and &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; about having so much control
over hardware. Working without an OS or a very simple RTOS gives you full confidence that if something isn&amp;rsquo;t working, it&amp;rsquo;s your
fault, and if you know the system well enough, you&amp;rsquo;ll know where to go to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debugging software on low-power hardware with limited FLASH space, especially if you need to disable some debugging optimizations
to make it fit on your hardware, is a real hassle sometimes. Debug prints are quite expensive operations, and if you&amp;rsquo;re trying to
solve a problem that&amp;rsquo;s affected by time, the debug prints may be &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this, though, will teach you a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dean Ween, of the rock band Ween, &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/zzYykIA1xVg?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=53&#34;&gt;once said&lt;/a&gt; the following when asked about why
they were recording their albums themselves on four-track cassette recorders instead of in a professional studio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you only have four tracks to record on, you have to write better songs&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limitations can be the greatest teacher of all. The domain of problems you have to solve are so immediate, so tangible, that
you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; you can find the answer if you look hard enough. I believe you can truly become one with your system, at least
more so than you ever could with the thousands of different devices with different operating systems and CPU architectures and
displays and input devices that are all capable of rendering this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a software engineer, especially early in your career, and you&amp;rsquo;re thinking about giving embedded a shot, I
highly recommend you do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>The Mead From Hell</title>
		<link>http://localhost:1313/blog/the-mead-from-hell/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 08:57:00 -0600</pubDate>
		
		<guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/the-mead-from-hell/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-if-i-handmade-christmas-gifts-this-year&#34;&gt;What if I handmade Christmas gifts this year?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oft-discussed &amp;ldquo;five love languages&amp;rdquo; concept includes gift giving as a
language of love. In middle school I remember we had to rank our love languages
from most preferred to least preferred, and if I remember right, gift giving
came out last. To this day, I&amp;rsquo;m not the biggeset fan of giving or receiving
gifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe I am a scrooge, a meiser, or an ahedonic post-capitalist (depending who
you ask), but I view myself as preferring practicality over everything. I&amp;rsquo;ve
got drawers filled with gifts that have never found a use, and even more drawers
filled with things I &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;d use eventually, and the idea of taking
anything out of those drawers and transferring them to a landfill where they
wont decompose until long after I do doesn&amp;rsquo;t sit well with me. I&amp;rsquo;m not trying
to lecture here; gift giving is a tradition that has permeated cultures for
thousands of years. I just feel like many of the gifts I&amp;rsquo;ve given in the past
have not been as useful as gold, frankincense, or myrrh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best gift I&amp;rsquo;ve ever received, bar none, is the water bottle that my sister
gave me all the way back in 2019. It has received more use than maybe any
object I&amp;rsquo;ve ever owned other than my smartphone. It&amp;rsquo;s saved the landfills
probably hundereds of pounds of plastic waste by now. It&amp;rsquo;s become a part of
my personality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make sure the gift was something that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t go to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-mead&#34;&gt;Why Mead?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mead is a weird choice for a gift, but it came after I realized the following
things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have equipment to brew beer already&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More people will like a sweet honey drink than beer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can reuse the bottles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You likely didn&amp;rsquo;t already receive mead for Christmas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How hard can it be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;quite-hard-actually&#34;&gt;Quite hard, actually&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mead is one of the easiest forms of alcohol to create. So easy, in fact, that it
can happen on accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because mead at its roots is simply honey, water, and yeast. Mead was
likely discovered when honey was left in a barrel, the barrel got rained on,
and yeast from the environment joined the party. Some time later, one of our
great ancestors then drank  from this barrel and then decided it was time for
some Friday Night Football, even though he had no concept of Friday Night or
Football.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;rsquo;s possible to make mead in a barrel with entropy alone, then it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t
be too hard to make it with all my fancy autosiphons and glass carboys and
no-rinse cleansers and sorbates and metabisulfites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mead made me come to the realization that, at least when it comes to booze
production, I am sub-caveman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-recipe&#34;&gt;The Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided that since I was starting this brew in November, peak apple season, I
could make a cyser instead of a straight mead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;cyser (n.)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;a mead that also contains apples&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NF1dhaeysB0&#34;&gt;this recipe on YouTube from Man Made Mead&lt;/a&gt;
on an apple-cinnamon cyser. The  cinnamon scored this recipe bonus Christmas points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1---november-7-2023&#34;&gt;Day 1 - November 7, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sanitize everything with one tablespoon of One Step Cleaner per gallon of warm water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pour 2.5 gallons of apple juice into a 6-gallon carboy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pour 2.5 gallons of distilled water into a 6-gallon carboy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add 5 pounds of honey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actually, add about 3 more pounds of honey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to add more honey to increase the ABV (alcohol by volume) to
something closer to  &amp;gt;10%. The original recipe aimed for about 6-7%, but at the last
minute, I decided to make this a still mead instead of a sparking mead like the
recipe states. This is because I needed to backsweeten the mead, but if I wanted
to have the mead ferment in the bottle to become carbonated, I would have to
backsweeten with a non-fermentable sweetner like erythritol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;backsweeten (v.)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;to add sugar back into a fermented beverage after the yeast have eaten all the
initial sugar during fermentation&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there was too much fermentable sugar in the bottle, and with a yeast with such
high alcohol tolerance, I could very easily have too much fermentation happen
in a sealed glass bottle. If that happens, I would have created a pantry filled
with cinnamon-apple-flavored glass bombs. It felt too weird to add  artificial
sweetner to something that&amp;rsquo;s filled with honey, so I decided against it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;foreshadowing (n.)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;a literary device used to suggest an event that will happen later in the story&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix all the ingredients together with a big plastic rod with expandable wings
attached to a drill you told your dad you were borrowing to help your friend
Tyler assemble a bedframe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siphon out a sample large enough to get a hydrometer reading, then write that down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix the yeast in warm water for 20 seconds as described in the yeast packet&amp;rsquo;s instructions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pour the yeast in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait, no, soak it for 20 minutes, not 20 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worry a little bit, Google a little bit, read that it&amp;rsquo;s probably going to be fine, proceed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the (sanitized) stopper and airlock on the carboy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set it in the back of your closet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/GoodnightSweetPrince.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Goodnight, sweet prince&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydrometer reading tells the specific gravity of the mead in its current,
unfermented state (called &amp;ldquo;must&amp;rdquo;). Specific gravity  means&amp;hellip;I don&amp;rsquo;t know
actually. I think it&amp;rsquo;s how thick the liquid is? (I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I could tell you
what makes a liquid &amp;ldquo;thick&amp;rdquo;.) In our case, it tells us how much sugar is in the
must right now so that once it&amp;rsquo;s done fermenting, we can calculate how much of
the sugar has been fermented and turned into alcohol. That will tell us the ABV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an original gravity (OG) of 1.071, should the yeast eat all the sugar and
turn it into alcohol, bringing the final gravity (FG) all the way back down
to 1.000, we can use the following formula to calculate the ABV of the final product:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ABV = (OG - FG) * 131.25&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ABV = (1.071 - 1.000) * 131.25 = 9.32%&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was aiming for a higher ABV, but I used literally all the honey I had in my home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-11---november-18-2023&#34;&gt;Day 11 - November 18, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The airlock on the carboy has all but stopped bubbling, bubbling only once every
several minutes, so I decided it was time to start prepping the apples. This
is where my lovely girlfriend Emily enters this story. We went to Sam&amp;rsquo;s Club to
purchase 18lbs of apples and absolutely nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/ApplesLaidOut.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;The apples in question&#34;&gt;
(The varieties, for those wondering, were Gala, Cosmic Crunch, Honeycrisp, and
Fuji.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all the edible wax was boiled off of the apples, I sliced all the apples
with the apple slicer Emily was so kind to bring from her home, and as I was
slicing them, remembered I had purchased pectic enzyme to put on the apples
to help extract more juice. I realized I had no idea &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; one should put the
pectic enzyme on the apples, so I sent Emily down the rabbit hole for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily, who has never homebrewed in her life and I don&amp;rsquo;t even think has tried
mead before, scoured meadmaking forums and /r/mead and gave me all the
information she could find. She soon after started discovering a bunch of
techniques and recipes I had never heard of. It really warmed my heart to
see her take an interest in this. Ever since, she&amp;rsquo;s continued coming up
with new flavors we can try to brew. I hope the two of us will get to
make all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that same night, we cooked potato soup for our friend Lauren. Lauren,
who is a recipient of the mead I have secretly been fermenting under my
summer wardrobe, could not know why I had so much apple paraphanelia in
my kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lied and told her I wanted to try making apple juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said that sounds like the kind I&amp;rsquo;d be up to on a Saturday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-12---november-19-2023&#34;&gt;Day 12 - November 19, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I siphoned all the mead into a plastic bucket fermenter and mixed in
potassium metabisulfite (to prevent oxidation of the mead which can
produce off flavors) and potassium sorbate (to stop the yeast from
reproducing and eating the apple juice.) I then immediately dumped
all the apples into the bucket, sealed it up, and went about my day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Actually, I only was able to add about 13lbs of apples because the
bucket was overflowing.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, things are going well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-13---november-20-2023&#34;&gt;Day 13 - November 20, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are no longer going well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The airlock, which should be completely inactive since I stabilized
the mead yesterday, is going bananas. Somehow the mead began to
ferment again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing some searching, I found out that I had &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; properly
stabilized the mead. It turns out you have to wait 24 hours after
adding the stabilizing agents before they take effect. The yeast
repopulated quickly and were eating all my precious apple juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This left me with one choice: kill it with fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My concern was no longer with neutering the yeast, they had to
die. Now. The longer they lived, the less apple sugar would
make it into the final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read online that I needed to heat the mead to 150F for 20
minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/FirstPasteurization.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Cookin in the kitchen&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got to get my first taste of the concoction tonight. And
wow, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/FirstGlass.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;A treat&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was thinking that it would be far too dry to be enjoyable
in this state, but the apples were so sweet that it was
very delicious and apple forward. Since it had more time to
steep on the apples, I knew that it would only get better
with time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-21---november-28-2023&#34;&gt;Day 21 - November 28, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the apple extraction is done, it&amp;rsquo;s time to transfer
the mead to its final container and toss in some cinnamon.
It should only be in this container for a couple days, absorb
some spicey notes, then finally get bottled. Here is what the
apples looked like after it was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/Nasty.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Ew&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-23---november-30-2023&#34;&gt;Day 23 - November 30, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have sanitized all the bottles and filled them. 35 bottles
of delicious apple-cinnamon cyser are ready to go and be
gifted to my wonderful friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/BottledUp.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Finally&amp;hellip;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was quite the journey. With all the yeast mishaps, this
mead became more difficult than any of the beers I had made
in the past. It was an educational journey. I learned a lot
about myself, and how much Emily can lovingly tolerate my
nonsense. All that&amp;rsquo;s left is to finish this blog post,
print out labels, and deliver it to everyone in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-26---december-3-2023&#34;&gt;Day 26 - December 3, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a long, arduous month of brewing, I decided it was
finally time for me to kick back and crack open a bottle
of mead for myself. I earned this, after all. After all the
time, money, and effort I put into this, it was time I
give myself a gift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A gift, I did not receive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cracked open my first bottle, and the cork flew off with
a &lt;strong&gt;POW&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mead was still fermenting&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How? I heat stabilized it! I followed the directions! I
tried to castrate the yeast, then I tried to slaughter the
yeast, but it was back, and with a vengence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/Bubbles.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Bubbles &amp;gt;:(&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that all the precious apple juice has been turned
from sweet, sugary goodness into more alcohol. How much
more alcohol? I have no idea. I never took a specific gravity
reading after adding the apples because why would I? The
apples should have never affected the alcohol content. Because
of this, I can only guess the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; ABV of the mead. It&amp;rsquo;s
probably around 10.5-11% alcohol by volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How am I getting this number? Educated guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not doing any more math. I did enough already. The mead
is not only beyond carbonated, it&amp;rsquo;s completely dry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dry mead was the least of my problems, however. I got very
lucky that my glass bottles were thick enough to withstand
the pressure of the carbonation. If they
weren&amp;rsquo;t, I would have had 35 tightly-packed glass bombs
in the cupboard above my fridge. If any one of them shattered,
it&amp;rsquo;s very likely that the kinetic energy could have set off
another, and another, and another, leading to a sticky
chain reaction that would have forever raised the eyebrows
of future prospective landlords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was shaking as I took all the bottles down and &amp;ldquo;burped&amp;rdquo;
each one to let out the pressure. I was worried one may shatter
in my hands and shoot an eye out (the homebrewer&amp;rsquo;s A Christmas
Story).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me and my corneas, everything went well enough,
though I did lose about three bottles worth of mead from
the liquid that spewed out the bottles after opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-24---december-4-2023&#34;&gt;Day 24 - December 4, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to heat pasteurize &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/LastTime.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Last time&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I let this go for 30 minutes at 150F this time, as opposed
to 20 the last time. I checked the temperature with &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;
thermometers to ensure my tools were working correctly.
After sanitizing my bottling bucket and siphon, I put
all the mead back in the bucket one last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/blog/The-Mead-From-Hell/FillErUp.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Fill er up!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fix the dryness, I added about 2lbs of honey into
the mead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-26---december-6-2023&#34;&gt;Day 26 - December 6, 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sanitized all the bottles &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, and filled them
&lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;. Now armed with 32.5 bottles, it&amp;rsquo;s finally
Christmas time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;epilogue&#34;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this article was full of moaning, but I really
had a great time doing this. No regrets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making this mead was like raising a yeasty, sticky
child for a month, but now it&amp;rsquo;s no longer my problem.
Instead, it&amp;rsquo;s a fine memory for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a few people who got this mead early, before
this blog post was written.
Seeing their skepticism turn to enjoyment made this
all worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making the mead distribution list may have been the
hardest part of this whole process (yes, I know what
I&amp;rsquo;m saying). Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s easy for me to lose sight
of how much love is truly in my life. I can get distracted
and lose sight of how many wonderful, amazing, interesting
people I get to call my friends and family. I wish I could
give all of you more mead than I am able to. When all was
said and done, there were only a few bottles left over for
Emily and I (especially after the in-bottle fermentation
fiasco) because I had so many people to distribute this to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I had to make cuts. If you are a couple or my
immediate family, I wish I could have given you more than
I have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you all for being such positive forces in my life.
The last few years have been a time of considerable change
for me and have flown by faster than I could have ever
imagined. Just in the past year I have left a job; started
a new one; taken in an amazing cat, Gibby; moved; met my
lovely girlfriend; gave Gibby a new home; and
experienced the passing of my unspeakably special dog, Rudy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With how fast paced everything has been, I&amp;rsquo;m likely
forgetting things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all of you who have stuck with me, been comrades through
this exciting year as full of opportunity as vertigo:
thank you, and I love you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy the mead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas, and a happy New Year to you all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
